Partial Guide to the Memorial Library of Music Collection
Department of Special Collections
- The fallen angel. / BISHOP, SIR HENRY ROWLEY (1786-1855), MLM 87
  Original manuscript signed. 207 leaves (title-page, 406 pages) 24 X 3O1/2 cm. The complete score of the oratorio which, according to Grove, has never been performed. The manuscript has a printed title-page.
- Guy Mannering or The gipsey's prophecy. / BISHOP, SIR HENRY ROWLEY (1786-1855), MLM 88
  As performed at the Theatre Royal, Covent Garden, composed & arranged for the piano forte by Thos. Attwood and Henry R. Bishop... London, Goulding, D'Almaine, Potter [1816] At head of title: The overture, songs, duets, glees & choruses in the musical play of. First edition. The first operatic setting of a novel by Sir Walter Scott.
- Let not a bell be toll'd. / BISHOP, SIR HENRY ROWLEY (1786-1855), MLM 89
  The poetry by C. C. Clarke. Composed and dedicated to Miss Clara Novello by Henry R. Bishop, April, 1834. Original manuscript, signed twice. 4 leaves (title-page, as above, 6 pages music and text) 30 x 24 cm. Clara Novello (1818-1908) English singer was the daughter of Vincent Novello, founder of the music-publishing firm of Novello & Company.
- Melodies of various nations with symphonies and accompaniments by Henry R. Bishop. / BISHOP, SIR HENRY ROWLEY (1786-1855), MLM 90
  The words by Thomas Bayly, Esq.... London, Goulding, D'Almaine, Potter [1822] First edition.
- The Missle toe Bough / BISHOP, SIR HENRY ROWLEY (1786-1855), MLM 90A
  Composed and arranged by Henry R. Bishop. London, n.d.. 4 leaves, 5 p.
- [My pretty Jane] / BISHOP, SIR HENRY ROWLEY (1786-1855), MLM 91
  Manuscript with the title: ""The bloom is on the rye,"" signed. ca. 1830. Score for small orchestra and voice. 1 leaf (2 pages) 301/2 x 241/2 cm. S. J. Adair Fitzgerald, in his Stories of famous songs, gives a detailed and amusing account of the story behind this ""most profitable song ever issued."" The words are by Edward Fitz-Ball.
- Native land or Return from slavery. / BISHOP, SIR HENRY ROWLEY (1786-1855), MLM 92
  Opera in three acts, performed at the Theatre Royal, Covent Garden. Composed and arranged for the voice & piano forte by Henry R. Bishop... With selections from Zingarelli, Boieldieu and Rossini... London, Goulding, D'Almaine [ca. 1824] First edition. inscribed to Miss Paton by the composer.
- L'Arlésienne. / BIZET, ALEXANDRE CESAR LEOPOLD, called GEORGES (1838-1875), MLM 93
  Drame en 3 actes de Alphonse Daudet, musique de Georges Bizet. Partition chant & piano... Paris, Choudens [1872] P1. no. A. C. L 2484. First edition. Presented for the first time at Paris, October 1, 1872. In his L'Arlésienne and Carmen, Bizet produced two works which contributed abundantly to the purification of the musical atmosphere in France and to the health of the lyric theater.
- L'Arlésienne. / BIZET, ALEXANDRE CESAR LEOPOLD, called GEORGES (1838-1875), MLM 94
  Drame en 3 actes de Alphonse Daudet, musique de Georges Bizet. Partition chant & piano transcrite par l'auteur. Paris, Choudens Père & Fils [1872] P1. no. A. C. 2484. Second edition. With changes in score. Wotquenne, 2605.
- Carmen. / BIZET, ALEXANDRE CESAR LEOPOLD, called GEORGES (1838-1875), MLM 95
  Opéra comique en 4 actes. Tiré de la nouvelle de Prosper Mérimée. Poéme de H. Meilhac et L. Halévy. Musique de Georges Bizet. Partition chant et piano arrangée par l'auteur. Paris, Choudens Père et Fils [1875] P1. no. A. C. 3082. First edition. At foot of p. [iii]: Paris, Imp: Aròuy, rue du Delta, 26. The first edition published as an opéra-comique has spoken dialogue. In the second edition the dialogue was replaced by twenty-six pages of recitatives composed by Ernest Guiraud. Bizet died within three months of the first performance. Presented for the first time at Paris, March 3, 1875.
- Carmen. / BIZET, ALEXANDRE CESAR LEOPOLD, called GEORGES (1838-1875), MLM 96
  Opéra en quatre actes. Tiré de la nouvelle de Prosper Mérimée. Poëme de H. Meilhac & L. Halévy. Musique de Georges Bizet. Partition chant et piano transcrite par l'auteur. Paris, Choudens Fils [1875] P1. no. A. C. 3082. Second edition. At foot of p. 363: Paris, Imp. E. Dupré, rue du Delta, 26. Wotquenne, 2606.
- Carmen. / BIZET, ALEXANDRE CESAR LEOPOLD, called GEORGES (1838-1875), MLM 97
  Opéra en 4 actes. Tiré de la nouvelle de Prosper Mérimée. Poéme de H. Meilhac et L. Halévy. Musique de Georges Bizet. Partition chant et piano arrangée par l'auteur. Paris, Choudens Père et Fils [1877] P1. no. A. C. 3554 At head of title: Paroles italiennes de A. de Lauzières, à Jules Pasdeloup, paroles alles allemandes de D. Louis. First edition with Italian and German text. Inscribed by the publishers to Mme. Galli-Marié and to Myriam Goestchel by Carmen Galli-Marié. Mme. Galli-Marié has written in a French version of the text for a considerable part of the score and has also made profuse notes throughout as to the rendition of the title role.
- Carmen. / BIZET, ALEXANDRE CESAR LEOPOLD, called GEORGES (1838-1875), MLM 98
  Opéra comique en 4 actes [par] Georges Bizet. Ballet. Paris, Choudens [1875] P1. no. A. C. 3273. Firstedition. The ballet for the first act of Carmen was issued as a supplement to the first edition of the opera itself.
- Djamileh. / BIZET, ALEXANDRE CESAR LEOPOLD, called GEORGES (1838-1875), MLM 99
  Opéra comique en un acte de Louis Gallet. Musique de Georges Bizet. Partition chant et piano réduite par I'auteur. Paris, Choudens [ca. 1872] P1. no. A. C. 2380. First edition. This copy belonged to Victor Massé and has his signature on the cover. Presented for the first time at Paris, May 22, 1872. Wotquenne, 2604.
- Feuilles d'album. / BIZET, ALEXANDRE CESAR LEOPOLD, called GEORGES (1838-1875), MLM 100
  Musique de Georges Bizet... Paris, Heugel [1867] P1.nos. H 3366, H 3367(2), H 3369, H 3370, H 3368(1), H 3371. Firstedition. Inscribed to Marie Bronthe by the composer. Contents: ""A une fleur,"" Alfred de Musset; ""Adieux à Suzon,"" Alfred de Musset; ""Sonnet,"" Ronsard; ""Guitare,"" Victor Hugo; ""Rose d'amour,"" Millevoye; ""Le grillon,"" Lamartine. Piano and vocal score. Wotquenne, 233.
- Vingt mélodies pour chant et piano par Georges Bizet. / BIZET, ALEXANDRE CESAR LEOPOLD, called GEORGES (1838-1875), MLM 101
  Paris, Choudens [ca. 1872] P1. no. A.C. 2486. First edition. inscribed to Victor Massé by the composer. Edition for mezzo-soprano or baritone.
- Les pêcheurs de perles. / BIZET, ALEXANDRE CESAR LEOPOLD, called GEORGES (1838-1875), MLM 102
  Opéra en 3 actes de M. Carré & Cormon. Musique de Georges Bizet. Partition chant et piano arrangée par l'auteur... Paris, Choudens [ca. 1863] P1. no. A.C. 992. First edition. Charles Gounod's copy with his signature. Presented for the first time at Paris, September 30, 1863. Wotquenne, 2602.
- Tarantella par Georges Bizet. / BIZET, ALEXANDRE CESAR LEOPOLD, called GEORGES (1838-1875), MLM 103
  Paris, G. Hartmann [ca.1870] P1. no. G. H. 343. First edition. Inscribed to Marie Bronthe by the composer. See also ASCHER, JOSEPH (1829-1869) Mazurka des traineaux; GALSWORTHY, JOHN (1867-1933) Carmen; GOUNOD, CHARLES FRANCOIS (1818-1893) La nonne sanglante; MASSE, FELIX MARIE (1822-1884) Le fils du brigadier; REYER, ERNEST (1823-1909) La statue.
- Macbeth. / BLOCH, ERNEST (1880-), MLM 104
- Trois poèmes juifs pour grand orchestre, a, danse; b, rite; c, cortège funèbre. / BLOCH, ERNEST (1880-), MLM 105
- Amphion Anglicus. / BLOW, JOHN (1649-1708), MLM 106
  A work of many compositions, for one, two, three and four voices with several accompagnements of instrumental musick and a Library thorow-bass to each song: figur'd for an organ, harpsichord, or theorboe-lute, by Dr. John Blow. London, Printed by William Pearson, for the author; and -are to be sold at his house and by Henry Playford, 1700. First edition. Inserted at front is a copy of the prospectus, dated 1699, with a receipt at the foot filled in and signed by the composer. Inserted at end is an engraving of Blow's monument in Westminster Abbey. Hirsch, III, 656.
- Anthems with introductory symphony. / BLOW, JOHN (1649-1708), MLM 107
  Original manuscript signed. 1683. 14 leaves (27 pages) 201/2 x 32cm. John Blow was one of the first choir boys of the Chapel Royal after the organ and choir were again admitted to the service of the Anglican C0hurch. He became organist of Westminster Abbey at the age of twenty and five years later a Gentleman of the Chapel Royal eventually becoming one of the three organists for this group. Purcell took Blow's place as organist at Westminster Abbey in 1679 but Blow returned to this post after the death of his famous pupil in 1695.
- La dame blanche. / BOIELDIEU, FRANCOIS ADRIEN (1775-1834), MLM 108
  Opéra comique en trois acres. Paroles de Mr. Scribe. Mis en musique et dédié à Son Altesse Royale, Madame Duchesse de Berry par A. Boieldieu... Paris, Janet et Cotelle [ca. 1827] P1. no. 2002. First edition. Orchestral score. Presented for the first time at Paris, December 10, 1825. Wotquenne, 1401.
- Autograph letter signed. / BOIELDIEU, FRANCOIS ADRIEN (1775-1834), MLM 108A
  To M. Fournier, n. p., ca. 1827, in which he mentions La dame blanche, his principal work.
- Autograph letter signed. / BOIELDIEU, FRANCOIS ADRIEN (1775-1834), MLM 108B
  To M. Fournier, Paris, November 20, 1833, in which he refers to his uneasiness over the bankruptcy of the Opéra-Comique, the expulsion of Charles X from whom he had received a pension, and his poor health.
- Autograph letter signed. / BOIELDIEU, FRANCOIS ADRIEN (1775-1834), MLM 108C
  To [Joseph August] Roeckel. Paris, May 3, 1830.
- [Galop] / BOIELDIEU, FRANCOIS ADRIEN (1775-1834), MLM 109
  Original manuscript with the title ""Premier intention du galop pour l'opéra, no. 16."" Signed. 1834. 1 leaf (1 page) 261/2 x 171/2 cm.
- Mefistofele. / BOITO, ARRIGO (1842-1918), MLM 110
  Opera di Arrigo Boito. Rappresentato a! Teatro Comunitativo di Bologna il 4 ottobre 1875. Canto e pianoforte. Riduzione di M. Saladino...Milano, Ricordi [1893] P1. no. 44720. First edition. Inscribed by the composer and by Sir George Henschel, first conductor of the Boston Symphony Orchestra and at the time of the inscription, June 6, 1893, conductor of the London Symphony Concerts. Presented for the first time at Milan, March 5, 1868. Wotquenne, 3192. Inserted is an autograph letter signed [to Paul Milliet] Quinte près Genève, April 19 [no year] in which he mentions ""Mephisto de Liege.""
- Nerone, tragedia in quattro atti di Arrigo Boito." / BOITO, ARRIGO (1842-1918), MLM 111
  Riduzione per canto e pianoforte di Ferruccio Calusio... Milano, G. Ricordi, c1924. P1. no. 119599. First edition. Inserted is an autograph letter. To the president of the Circolo Sociale di Triento, Milan, December 30, 1899.
- Astartus / BONONCINI, GIOVANNI BATTISTA (1672-1750), MLM 112
  An opera as it was perform'd at the Kings Theatre for the Royal Academy. Compos'd by Bononcini. London, I. Walsh and I. Hare [ca. 1721] First edition. The text is by Paolo Antonio Rolli, altered from an earlier libretto by Apostolo Zeno and Pietro Pariati.
- The favourite songs in the opera call'd Calphurnia / BONONCINI, GIOVANNI BATTISTA (1672-1750), MLM 113
  [by] Bononcini. London, I. Walsh and Ino & Joseph Hare, 1724. First edition. A manuscript note on the title-page states that the words were written by Grazio Bracciola in 1713, altered by Haym, and set to music by Bononcini. It was first performed at the Royal Academy of Music, April 18, 1724, and had an uninterrupted run of nine nights. The score for the Italian version was by Johann David Heinichen. Wotquenne, 5428.
- The favourite songs in the opera call'd Crispus. / BONONCINI, GIOVANNI BATTISTA (1672-1750), MLM 114
  London, I. Walsh [1722] First edition. Orchestral score.
- For the birthday of the Sweet Angel," / BONONCINI, GIOVANNI BATTISTA (1672-1750), MLM 115
  November the 23rd 1731: Vivace, Andante, Gavotta, Marcha, Sarabanda, Gigna, 1-Menuet, 2-Menuet. A suite of eight movements. Full score and parts for first and second violins and bass. Original manuscript. 10 leaves (title-page as above, 16 pages) 231/2 x 301/4 cm. With Musique pastorale pour le 23 novembre 1730.
- Griselda / BONONCINI, GIOVANNI BATTISTA (1672-1750), MLM 116
  An opera as it was perform'd at the Kings Theatre for the Royal Accademy. Compos'd by Mr. Bononcini. London, I. Walsh [1722] First edition. Orchestral score. Text by Paolo Rolli after Zeno. Presented for the first time at London, February 22, 1722. Wotquenne, 5457.
- Musique pastorale pour le 23 novembre 1730. / BONONCINI, GIOVANNI BATTISTA (1672-1750), MLM 117
  Jour de la naissance de Lady Mary Godolphin: Le triomphe, La marche, Dance de nimphes, Une gigue, V Menuet gay, Menuet doux, La follette, autre Menuet. A suite of eight movements. Full score and parts for first and second violins and bass. Original manuscript. 20 leaves (title-page as above, 3 pages part-titles, 28 pages) 221/2 x 271/2, 231/2 x 301/4 cm. With this is a photograph of the composer's portrait in the Royal College of Music. See also Scarlatti, Alessandro (1660-1725) Thomyris.
- Songs in the new opera call'd Almahide. / BONONCINI, MARC ANTONIO (1675-1726), MLM 118
  The songs done in Italian & English as they are perform'd at ye Queens Theatre. [London] I. Walsh [1710] First edition. Cf. Smith, Bibliography of musical work published by John Walsh, no. 344, p. 106.
- Songs in the new opera call'd Camilla / BONONCINI, MARC ANTONIO (1675-1726), MLM 119
  As they are perform'd at the Theatre Royall [London] I. Walsh [1706] First edition. The text is by Stampiglia. This opera enjoyed an extraordinary popularity. In England it ran sixty-four nights in four years. Eitner, II, 125; Smith, Bibliography of musical works published by John Walsh, no. 221, p. 70; Wolffheim, II, 1326 (1).
- Avril / BORDES, CHARLES (1863-1909), MLM 120
  Mélodie pour-mezzo-soprano avec accompagnement de piano. Poésie de Aimé Mauduit. Musique de Charles Bordes... Paris, J. Hamelle [1883] Cover-title. Pl. no. J. 2111. First edition. Inscribed to Emmanuel Chabrier by the composer.
- Madrigal à la musique. / BORDES, CHARLES (1863-1909), MLM 121
  Henry VIII de Shakespeare. Traduction de Maurice Bouchor. Choeur mixte sans accompagnement. Mis en musique par Ch. Bordes... Paris, E. Baudoux [1895] P1. no. E. B. et Cie. 231. First edition. Inscribed to Paul Soujoud by the composer.
- 3 mélodies. / BORDES, CHARLES (1863-1909), MLM 122
  Poésie de Jean Lahor. No. 1. Chanson triste... [Musique de] Charles Bordes. Op: 8. Paris, Bruneau [ca. 1887] P1. no. B. & Cie. 106. First edition. Inscribed to Thérèse Roger by the composer.
- Trois danses béarnaises pour orchestre par Charles Bordes. / BORDES, CHARLES (1863-1909), MLM 123
  Op. 11. Réduction à 4 mains par l'auteur... Paris, Lissarrague [ca. 1888] P1. no. A. L. 636 bis. First edition. Inscribed to Mlle. Thérèse Roger, to whom the work is dedicated, by the composer.
- The Bogatyrs. / BORODIN, ALEXANDER PORPHYRIEVITCH (1833-1887), MLM 124
  Manuscript fragment signed. September 9, 1867. 1 leaf (1 page) 251/4 x 24 cm. This is a sketch for the tavern scene from Borodin's unpublished opera.
- Le Prince Igor. / BORODIN, ALEXANDER PORPHYRIEVITCH (1833-1887), MLM 125
  Opéra en quatre actes avec prologue. Paroles et -musique de A. Borodine. Réduction pour chant et piano... Texte: russe, français et allemand. Traduction française de M. Jules Ruelle, allemande de Mme. Alexandroff... Leipzig, M. P. Belaieff, 1889. At head of title: title, etc. in Russian. P1. nos. 119, 120, et al. First edition.
- Duetto per violoncello e contrabasso. / BOTTESINI, GIOVANNI (1821-1889), MLM 126
  Original manuscript. 20 leaves (40 pages) 301/2 x 24 cm. Bottesini autographs are very rare and this unpublished score of the duetto for violoncello and double bass reflects the technical capacities of two artists (Bottesini and Piatti) who had no rival
- Alcestis. / BOUGHTON, RUTLAND (1878-), MLM 127
  A choral drama adapted from the play of Euripides. Englished by Gilbert Murray. Musicked by Rutland Boughton. Original manuscript signed. Finished June 3, 1922. 101 leaves (202 pages including title-page as above) 231/2 x 371/2 cm. Boughton's works reflect an effort to extend the theories of Wagner and at the same time to simplify the operatic idiom to suit popular taste and understanding.
- The queen of Cornwall. / BOUGHTON, RUTLAND (1878-), MLM 128
  Play by Thomas Hardy... Set as a music-drama by Rutland Boughton. London, Joseph Williams [c1926] P1. no. J. W. 16279. First edition. Piano and vocal score. Thomas Hardy's copy with a label reading: ""From the library of Thomas Hardy, O. M. Max Gate"" inside front-cover. Presentation copy from the publisher signed ""Florian Williams, Dec. 1926.""
- Cantique. / BOULANGER, NADIA (1887-), MLM 129
  Poésie de Maurice Maeterlinck. Musique de Nadia Boulanger. Paris, J. Hamelle, c1999 [caption-title] P1. no. J. 6840 H. Inscribed to Mme. Chéreau by the composer.
- Chanson. / BOULANGER, NADIA (1887-), MLM 130
  Paroles de Georges Delaquys. Musique de Nadia Boulanger Paris, J. Hamelle, c1914. P1. no. J. 6812 H. Caption title. inscribed to Mme. Chéreau by the composer.
- Versailles. / BOULANGER, NADIA (1887-), MLM 131
  Poésie de Albert Samain. Musique de Nadia Boulanger. Paris, J. Hamelle, c1914. P1. no. J. 6808 H. Caption title. Inscribed to Mme. Chéreau by the composer.
- Le carnaval d'Athènes. / BOURGAULT-DUCOUDRAY, LOUIS ALBERT (1840-1910), MLM 132
  Danses grecques pour le piano à 4 mains par L. A. Bourgault-Ducoudray... Paris, Henry Lemoine [ca. 1890] P1. no. B. D. #. First edition. lnscribed to Mme. E. Turquet by the composer.
- La conjuration des fleurs / BOURGAULT-DUCOUDRAY, LOUIS ALBERT (1840-1910), MLM 133
  Partition chant & piano. Paris, Huegel & Fils [ca. 1883] P1. no. H. 5731. First edition. Inscribed: ""A Monsieur Morel, en souvenir de l'exécution au 22 mai 1894 au succès de laquelle il a grandament contribué par la belle interprétation de rôle du Génie. Son bien devoue et très reconnaissant. Bourgault-Ducoudray.""
- Thamara. / BOURGAULT-DUCOUDRAY, LOUIS ALBERT (1840-1910), MLM 134
  Opéra en quatre tableaux. Poème de Louis Gallet. Musique de L. A. Bourgault-Ducoudray. Partition réduite pour chant & piano par Van den Heuvel... Paris, Léon Grus, 1892. P1. no. L. G. 4631. First edition. Inscribed to [Victor] Warot by the composer. Presented for the first time at Paris, December 28, 1891. Wotquenne, 2639.
- The chaplet. / BOYCE, WILLIAM (1710-1779), MLM 135
  A musical entertainment, as it is perform'd at the Theatre-Royal in Drury-Lane. Compos'd by Dr. Boyce. London, I. Walsh [ca. 1750] First edition. The text is by Moses Mendez. Eitner, II, 163; Wolffheim, II, 1327.
- The shepherds' lottery. / BOYCE, WILLIAM (1710-1779), MLM 136
  A musical entertainment. As it is perform'd at the Theatre-Royal in Drury Lane. Compos'd by Dr. Boyce. London, I. Walsh [1751] First edition. The text is by Moses Mendez. Wotquenne, 3595.
- [Tragic overture, opus 81]" / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 137
  The original manuscript signed with the caption-title ""Tragische Ouverture."" 28 leaves (56 pages) 35 X 27 cm. Inserted, at the front, is a photograph of the composer with his signature. [See negative microfilm of each page single.] The Tragic overture
- Concert für violine mit Begleitung des Orchesters von Johannes Brahms. / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 138
  Op. 77... Berlin, N. Simrock, 1879. Pl. 110. 8133. First edition. Cf. Geiringer, Brahms. His life and work, New York, 1947.
- An autograph letter signed. / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 138A
  To an unidentified correspondent, n.p., n.d. Translation: Honored and dear young lady: Tendering you my best thanks for the friendliness with which you keep me in mind, I send you herewith the desired portrait. It has been rather long in coming because I was unwilling to send it without being able to enclose the second picture with which Joachim sends his best regards. I very much hope the summer will again bring you to the Rhine and I shall then have the pleasure of seeing you again. With cordial greetings to you and Miss Leser, Your devoted Joh. Brahms
- Ein deutsches Requiem nach Worten der Heil. Schrift für Soli, Chor und Orchester (Orgel ad libitum) componirt von Johannes Brahms." / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 139
  Op. 45. Leipzig, J. Rieter-Biedermann [ca. 1868-1869] P1. no. 593. First edition. Piano and vocal score. Hirsch, IV, 715; Wotquenne, 747. This is the composer's greatest choral work. It occupied him at intervals for more than ten years. The second movement, originally intended as a part of the projected Symphony in D minor (the later Pianoforte concerto, op. 15) was composed 1857-1859. In the autumn of 1861 Brahms arranged this as a cantata in four movements. The work remained in this preparatory stage for four years. In 1865 he took it up again and by August 1866 had completed movements one, two, three, four, six and seven. The fifth was composed in May 1868.
- An autograph letter signed. / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 139A
  signed by Clara Schumann, to an unidentified friend, written from Baden-Baden on May 9, 1869, in which reference is made to the performance of Brahms's Requiem at Karlsruhe.
- Romanzen und Lieder für eine oder zwei Stimmen mit Begleitung des Pianoforte von Johannes Brahms. / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 140
  Op. 84. Nos. 1-5. Somerabend [words by] Hans Schmidt. Berlin, N. Simrock, 1882. P1. no. 8295. First edition.
- An autograph letter signed. / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 140A
  To Fritz Simrock, Rome, April 24, 1881.
- Serenade für kleines Orchester (Blasinstrumente, Violen, Violoncelli, u. Bässe) von Johannes Brahms." / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 141
  Op. 16. Partitur... Bonn, N. Simrock [1860] Pl. no. 6129. First edition. Inscribed by the composer: ""Der besten Freundin Clara, Weihnacht, 1860.""
- An autograph letter signed. / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 141A
  n. p., n. d. Translation: Dear Elise: Fortunately Mother and Christian have been kind enough to write about you-unfortunately not as favorably as I should wish. I hope very much that the news will soon be better and that you will write me so yourself. It
- Ungarische Tänze [1-3] für Orchester gesetzt von Johannes Brahms. / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 142
  Partitur... Berlin, N. Simrock [1869] Pl. no. 7455. First edition. Wotquenne, 7263.
- An engraved portrait. / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 142A
  by Hollyer.
- Ungarische Tänze [1-3] / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 143
  Original manuscript signed. 17 leaves (33 pages) 321/2 x 26 cm. The Hungarian Dances are proof of Brahms's versatility as a creative artist. They achieved an unparalleled success. Brahms contrived, while preserving the characteristic melody, harmony, and rhythm of gypsy music, to give it an artistic form which raised it to a higher level.
- [Nine songs, opus 32,no. 1]" / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 144
  Wie rafft ich mich auf in der Nacht. Original manuscript. 1864. V. 2 leaves (3 pages) 33 x 251/2 cm. The text is by August, Count of Platen-Hallermund. Brahms probably found the model for this noble song in Schubert's works. It is reminiscent of certain songs for Winterreise such as ""Estarrung"" which expresses a similar mood. ""The opening number of Op. 32, Wie rafft ich mich auf [in der Nacht] is a powerful composition. With its dramatic entry, its tremendous climax, and the wonderful interlocking of the voice and the almost symphonic accompaniment, it rivals the greatest songs of the later Schubert, by whom Brahms is here perceptibly influenced"" (Geiringer, Brahms. His life and work, Oxford, 1947).
- Zwei Gesänge für eine Altstimme mit Bratsche und Pianoforte von Johannes Brahms. / BRAHMS, JOHANNES (1833-1897), MLM 145